Sarah Scudder Lyon Papers, 1867-1966 (bulk 1923-1944)
Sophia Smith Collection
Sarah Scudder Lyon papers
1867-1966
1923-1944
Lyon, Sarah Scudder, 1895-1966
MS 609
1 box (.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
YWCA executive. Papers are primarily related to her work in the Foreign Division of the Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A., 1923-1944. Types of materials include correspondence, photographs, reports, a scrapbook, speeches, travel notes, and writings. A large portion documents Lyon's overseas travels for the YWCA through reports and more informal "diary letters."
Sarah Scudder Lyon was born November 8, 1884, in Summit, New Jersey, to Sarah Johnson Wood and Phoebus W. Lyon. She prepared for college at Ivy Hall School in Bridgeton, New Jersey (1898-1902). Lyon attended Mount Holyoke College in South Hadley, Massachusetts, from 1902-06, earning an A.B. in biology and Latin.
Her long career with the YWCA began in 1905 when she took a job as a Secretary in the East End Branch of the Bridgeport, Connecticut, YWCA. She attended the American Committee's Chicago Training Institute in 1906, then went to work as an Industrial Secretary in the YWCA of Akron, Ohio (1906-07). She returned to Mount Holyoke for one year as Student Secretary (1907-08) then became General Secretary in Akron (1908-1916) and Field Secretary at the College of Wooster, in Wooster, Ohio (1916-17).
Lyon joined the YWCA of the U.S.A. national staff in New York City as Executive of the headquarters staff of the Overseas Committee of the War Work Council late in 1917. After the reconstruction period, Lyon was made Association Executive of the Foreign and Overseas Department (1920-23) and then Executive of the newly re-named Foreign Division, a position she held until her retirement in 1944.
In this capacity, Lyon traveled extensively, conferring and consulting with YWCA leadership and staff in more than fifty countries. She also often represented the YWCA of the U.S.A. at international meetings, including World YWCA Councils and three world meetings of the Executive Committee of the International Missionary Council, as well as its significant Jerusalem Conference in 1928.
During her years with the Foreign Division, Lyon completed an M.A. (1932) and did coursework toward a Ph.D. in international relations at Columbia University. Her thesis, "The Connection of the Foreign Division of the Young Women's Christian Association with Governments," drew heavily on her work experience. "When she did graduate work in international relations at Columbia, one wonders whether Sarah Lyon or the instructors profited more," wrote Emma Bailey Speer in a retirement tribute.
After retiring from the YWCA, Lyon served as Executive Director (1946-53) of the Vellore Christian Medical College Board, a group of twenty Canadian and U.S. mission boards that served as the "home base service agency" of the missionary Medical College and Hospital in Vellore, South India.
In 1961 Lyon moved to Mt. San Antonio Gardens, a retirement community in Pomona-Claremont, California. She died there on February 5, 1981 after a long illness. Lyon's ashes were placed in the family plot in Green-Wood Cemetery in Brooklyn, New York.
The Sarah Scudder Lyon Papers consist of .5 linear ft. and are primarily related to her work in the Foreign Division of the Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A., 1923-44. Types of materials include correspondence, photographs, reports, a scrapbook, speeches, travel notes, and writings.
A large portion of the Papers documents Lyon's travels all over the world for the YWCA through both official reports and more informal "diary letters." A scrapbook with many photographs presented by the YWCA of Manila, Philippines, when Lyon visited there in 1932 is included.
Other materials of note include a set of circular letters (1929-44) sent several times a year to American YWCA staff stationed around the world. These letters are full of news about Foreign Division colleagues, the doings of the national association, and life and events in the U.S. There are also copies of articles Lyon wrote for the YWCA's general magazine, Association Monthly/Womans Press, 1919-45.
The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
The Sarah Scudder Lyon Papers came to the Sophia Smith Collection with the Records of the YWCA of the U.S.A. in 2002. Sarah Lyon donated them to the YWCA in 1979.
Lyon, Sarah Scudder, 1895-1966; International relations -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. -- History -- Sources
Related materials, including Lyon's M.A. thesis, "The Connection of the Foreign Division of the Young Women's Christian Association with Governments," are in the YWCA USA Records, Sophia Smith Collection. The Edith Lerrigo Papers contain correspondence and notes on a conversation Lerrigo had with Lyon about her work for the YWCA as part of a project to collect reminiscences of retired Foreign Secretaries.
- Biographical materials, 1900-circa 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Mount Holyoke College, circa 1906-56 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Photographs, 1862-1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- YWCA of Akron, Ohio, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- YWCA of the U.S.A.
  - General, 1920-80 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Articles for Association Monthly and Womans Press, 1919-45 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Foreign Division
    - General, 1923-44 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
    - Report of summer in Europe, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Report of Miss Sarah S. Lyon's Visit to the Orient," Aug-Nov 1933 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Report of Miss Sarah S. Lyon's Field Trip," Jul-Dec 1936 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Circular "pastoral" letters to overseas staff, 1929-44 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - "Diary Letter" travel notes
      - 1920 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Dec 1922-Jan 1923 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Mar-Jun 1928 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Jul-Nov 1933 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Jun-Dec 1936 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Scrapbook presented by YWCA of Manila, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Speeches
      - "Trends and Problems of the Foreign Division," Feb 1930 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - "The Newer Concept of a North American Missionary Program as a Part of the World Project," Foreign Missions Conference, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Writings
  - General, 1917-74 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Book reviews, 1965-70 (Box 1, Folder 23)